<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The consideration of a position concerning the Book of common-prayer as also of some particulars held forth for truths by one Edmund Elis, stiled a minister of the Gospel of Jesus Christ : with a warning of tender bowels to the rulers, teachers and people of this nation concerning their church and ministry : likewise a few words concerning the kingdom, laws and government of Christ in the heart and conscience, its inoffensiveness to all just laws and governments of the kingdoms of men / by Isaac Penington the younger.</title>
            <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10759186</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10759186</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54031)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1407:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The consideration of a position concerning the Book of common-prayer as also of some particulars held forth for truths by one Edmund Elis, stiled a minister of the Gospel of Jesus Christ : with a warning of tender bowels to the rulers, teachers and people of this nation concerning their church and ministry : likewise a few words concerning the kingdom, laws and government of Christ in the heart and conscience, its inoffensiveness to all just laws and governments of the kingdoms of men / by Isaac Penington the younger.</title>
                  <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
                  <author>Elys, Edmund, ca. 1634-ca. 1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elys, Edmund, ca. 1634-ca. 1707.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45699:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45699:1"/>
            <p>THE CONSIDERATION OF A POSITION Concerning the Book of Common-Prayer, AS ALSO Of ſome Particulars held forth for Truths, by one EDMUND ELIS, ſtiled a Miniſter of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>With a Warning of Tender Bowels to the Rulers, Teachers and People of this Nation, concerning their Church and Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe a few Words concerning the Kingdom, Laws and Government of Chriſt in the Heart and Conſcience; it's Inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiveneſſe to all Juſt Laws and Governments of the Kingdoms of men.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iſaac Penington</hi> the Younger.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Behold, I come as a Thief. Bleſſed is he that watcheth, and keepeth his Garments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 16.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> &amp; <hi>Wind-Mill</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:45699:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45699:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>CHRIST, the Eternal Son of God, the ſubſtance of all the Types and Shadows of the Law, was made a Prieſt to God, <hi>not after the Law of a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Commandment, but after the Power of an endleſs Life.</hi> He came in the Power of the Father, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Power, he miniſtred the Power and in the Power. Thus he gathered together living ſtones, built them into a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Temple for the Father of life to dwell in, that they might be filled with the Power, dwell in the Power, and be to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Power. The Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Church of the Old Teſtament, the Church of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> was gathered by the Letter, was to be ordered by the Letter, was to keep and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Law of the Letter, was to have Prieſts and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices according to the Letter: but the New Teſtament Church was to be of true Jews, of Jews gathered in the Power, Circumciſed by the Power, renewed in the Power, &amp;c. So that he is not a Jew any longer, who is one outward, nor that Circumciſion, which is outward in the fleſh; but he is a Jew, which is one inwardly, and Circumciſion is that of the heart in the Spirit, and not in the Letter. We are the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſaith the Apoſtle, which Worſhip God in the Spirit, and have no confidence in the fleſh. The New-Teſtament <pb facs="tcp:45699:3"/> ſtate is a ſtate of ſubſtance, even of that ſpiritual ſubſtance, which the Law held out in ſhadows. The Jew is inward, the Circumciſion inward, the Sacrifices inward, the Church inward, the Miniſtry inward, the Worſhip inward: all is in Spirit, in Life, in Power, in Vertue; the whole ſtate is anſwerable to the High Prieſt of our Profeſſion, even <hi>after the Power of the endleſs life.</hi> By the Eternal Spirit was he made a Miniſter, by it he preached (<hi>the Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anointed me to preach the Goſpel, &amp;c.</hi> Luke <hi>4.18.</hi>) through it he offered up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Sacrifice without ſpot to God, <hi>Heb. 9.14.</hi> and in the ſame Power runs the vein of the whole diſpenſation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, for it is a <hi>miniſtration of the Spirit, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>3.8.</hi> Take away the Life, take away the Spirit, ye take away the ſtones of this Building, ye take away the Church, ye take away the Miniſtry, ye take away all.</p>
            <p>Now about this inward Building there was an outward Court, which had its Being, State, and Honour from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the inward life. The vertue of the inward Building did caſt a reflection, and bring forth an outward ſtate (as it cannot but do, where ever it appears in its riches and glory.) This ſtate ſtood firm in the dayes of the Apoſtles, till Gods mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring and removing of his Temple, Altar and Worſhippers, and his giving up of the outward Court (it having loſt the life and vertue, which flowed into it from the Temple, while the Temple remained within it) to the Gentiles, who under the Goſpel are ſuch as are Uncircumciſed in Spirit, &amp; can Worſhip in the outward Court without the Spirit. The enemy indeed fought hard againſt the Life and Power, but he could not there prevail, the Gates of Hell could not prevail againſt the true Church, which brought forth the Man-child, nor againſt the Man-child whom ſhe brought forth, but the Man-child was <pb facs="tcp:45699:3"/> caught up to God, and the Woman fled into the Wilderneſſe. Then that Church, State and Worſhip, which depended upon their preſence, was diſſolved: For how could it be otherwiſe, when both the Man-child, which was the Head of the Church (from whence the Vertue, Life and Influence did flow into the whole Body) and the Woman (or Church) her ſelf alſo vvere both gone out of ſight? So that the Miniſtry of Eternal life, &amp; the Temple, vvherein the life vvas miniſtred, being both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, they are neither of them henceforvvard to be found in that place, vvhere they vvere beheld before, (and vvhere moſt eyes vvould be ready to look for them again) but there vvhere the Spirit had hid them.</p>
            <p>Novv mark diligently, vvhat kind of eſteem the true Church hath had in the World, ever ſince her diſrobing her ſelf of her outvvard garments and flight into the Wilderneſs, and hovv her true Seed have been handled. The Dragon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly caſts a flood after her; her beautiful raiment being put off, and ſhe clothed in the habit of a Widovv, the eye of the World could no longer ſee and acknovvledge her to be the Church, but diſdain, reproach, revile her. This is her lot all the dayes of Antichriſt, ſhe is miſrepreſented by the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons flood of reproaches, and looked upon as a ſtrumpet, as one that pretends to Chriſt for her Lord and Husband, to his Spirit, to his Kingdom, to his Truth vvithout a juſt right, and the remnant of her Seed are ſtill made War vvith by the Dragon. Who have been the hunted ones, the hated, the perſecuted in all Nations, but the tender-conſcienced, vvho receive the Lavv of Chriſt into their hearts, bovving to him in their Worſhip and Converſation, and dare not bovv or Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip according to the Doctrines and Cammandments of men?</p>
            <p>Novv the true Church or Temple being thus removed, the outvvard Court becomes the Habitation and Place of Worſhip <pb facs="tcp:45699:4"/> among the Gentiles, all the time of the Churches abode in the Wilderneſs. The Spirit of the Lord having left it, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſpirit (man's earthly Nature and Wiſdom) the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Antichriſt enters into it, and upholds the Form of the former Building (ſo far as it judgeth neceſſary) and here it is found Worſhipping, and making a great ſhevv of Holineſs and devotion, but in the mean time makes War vvith the true Worſhippers, vvho cannot Worſhip in the outvvard Court (ſince the Spirit of the Lord hath left it and given it to the Gentiles) but follovv the Church into the Wilderneſs, and Worſhip in that Temple vvhich God hath removed thither.</p>
            <p>O vvhere is the eye vvhich can read theſe things, as they are vvritten either in the Letter, or in the Spirit. Antichriſt is a Myſtery of Iniquity, vvhich vvorks, and gets up, and reigns under an appearance of Godlineſs; and he that vvill diſcern him and his falſe vvayes of Worſhip, muſt have that eye, vvhich ſees beyond the appearance of things, into their nature: and in this is the Diſcovery of him, and the Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption from him. And happy is he, vvho is not <hi>defiled with Women,</hi> but abideth in the true <hi>Virginity,</hi> expecting and preparing for the appearance of the Bridegroom.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45699:4"/>
            <head>The CONSIDERATION of a POSITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON concerning the Book of COMMON-PRAYER; As alſo of ſome Particulars held forth for Truths,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THere is a Poſition laid down in ſome Printed Letters, concerning the uſe of the Common-Prayer-Book, tendred by one <hi>Edm. Elis</hi> (who profeſſeth himſelf to be a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt) to Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> (as he ſtileth them) againſt which Poſition he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth me, if I find upon my Spirit any thing to be objected againſt it, to diſcover it in exact and punctual expreſſions. This deſire of his is ſet down in Print after the Letters.</p>
            <p>His Poſition or Aſſertion is this: <hi>That a man may Worſhip God in Spirit, and in Truth in the uſe of that form of Prayer for Morning and Evening, which we call the Common-Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whoever would weigh this Aſſertion aright, muſt have the Ballance of the Sanctuary, and muſt put it into the Scale with an equal hand; and then looking with that eye, which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſee the Miſteries of the Kingdom of God, to him who is born of God, the Truth or Error of it is eaſily diſcerned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True Prayer is the breathing of the Child to the Father which begat it, from the ſence of its wants, for the ſupply of thoſe wants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Winde bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it cometh, and whither it goeth: So is every one that is born of the Spirit, John</hi> 3.8. God by the Breath of his Spirit, begets a man out of the Spirit and likeneſs of this World, into his own image and likeneſſe. He that is thus begotten: wants Nouriſhment, wants the Divine Warmth, the Breaſts of Conſolation, the Cloathing of the Spirit, the Garment of Salvation; wants the Bread of Life to feed on, wants the Water of Life to drink, wants ſtrength againſt the enemies Aſſaults, wiſdom againſt his Snares and Temptations, wants the arm of the Deliverer to preſerve and carry on the <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45699:5"/> work of Redemption daily, wants Faith to deny the fleſhly Wiſdom, that ſo he may Truſt and Feel the Vertue of the Arm of the Deliverer, wants Hope, Patience, Meekneſſe, a clear Guidance, an upright Heart to follow after the Lord: yea ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many are the daily wants of that which is begotten by the Breath of God, in its ſtate of weakneſſe, until it be drawn up into the Unity of the Body, where the full Communion with the Life is felt, the Heart ſatisfied, and the wants drowned.</p>
            <p>Now the breathing of this Child to the Father, from the ſence of theſe wants, for his Supply, that's Prayer: nay though it be but a Groan, or Sigh, which cannot be uttered or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet that's Prayer, true Prayer, which hath an acceptance with the Lord, and receiveth a Gracious Anſwer from him: And he that begetteth the Child, teacheth him to Pray, even by the ſame Spirit which begat him. In watching daily to the Spirit, the Child is kept ſenſible of the Will of the Father, and in his Light he ſees the Way wherein he is to walk, he ſees alſo the Enemie when he is coming, yea and the Snares he is privily laying, and he feels his own weakneſſe to withſtand or eſcape: And in this ſence his Heart cries to the Father of Spirits for Preſervation, for him to ſtand by him, for him to ſtep in in the needful time, even in the Seaſon of Diſtreſs. And thus, watching to the Spirit, the Life of a Chriſtian is a continual courſe of Prayer: <hi>He prayes continually.</hi> This is the Living Prayer of the Living Child, which conſiſts not in a Form of Words, either read out of a Book or conceived in the Mind; but in feeling the Breath of its Nature iſſuing out, from the Principle of Life in it, to the Living Spring, which is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it; who by cauſing his vertues to ſpring up in it, nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to Everlaſting Life.</p>
            <p>But now, man who is not born of the Spirit, but (by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſome of the Truths of God in the Wiſdom from below) hath attained to ſome change of Opinion and Converſation, he pretends to be this Birth from above, though indeed he is born but <hi>of Bloods,</hi> or <hi>of the Will of the fleſh,</hi> or <hi>of the Will of Man, John</hi> 1.13. and what God begets in, and gives to his True Child, he will be imitating, though he be out of the Nature and Spirit, where the True Child is begotten, and where the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45699:5"/> True gift of the Father is received by him. He will be believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though he hath not received any Proportion of the Living Faith from the Hand of the Father; he will be forming Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Sorrow for ſin, though his Heart be not turned from it; he will be hoping in Gods Mercy, although he be both from off the Foundation, and from under the ſhadow of the Mercy-ſeat; and he will be praying, though he hath neither received the Spirit, nor be taught by the Spirit to pray: And ſo being from that which ſhould guide him, and teach him the truth and way of Worſhip as it is in Jeſus, he runs out into the inventions and imaginations, and ſets up a way of his own chuſing; which he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving much conſidered of, and beat out by reaſonings, and fenced about with Arguments, he grows wiſe in his own eyes, and now verily believes it to be the way of God, and that he is able to maintain it againſt all oppoſers. Thus one man, he is for a Form; another man, he is againſt a Form, and for conceived prayers; and each think themſelves able to maintain their own, and to overthrow each other. But Oh that that ear were open, which can hear the truth, that where there is any true, honeſt, upright deſire after God, from the ſimplicity of the heart, it might not be thus betrayed through the ſubtilty of the fleſhly wiſdom, which lies lurking in the wiſe, reaſoning, knowing part, to betray the poor weak Babe. The natural man, the reaſoning man, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding man, the wiſe man according to the natural wiſdom, cannot underſtand the things of God. Here's no learning to pray aright, to believe aright, to hope aright, to mourn aright, to rejoyce aright, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this wiſdom muſt be brought to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.) and a man muſt become as a child to all knowledge, as let in this way: And he that ſo becomes a child, is taught to pray, to believe, to wait, to hope, and all that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to eternal life.</p>
            <p>Now as the Father teacheth to pray, ſo he giveth deſires or words (if he pleaſe) according to the preſent need. Sometimes he gives but ability to ſigh, or groan (if he give no more, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts that.) Sometimes he gives ſtrong breathings, and plenty of words to pour out the ſoul in before the Lord. But if a man ſhould catch thoſe words, and lay them up againſt another time, and offer them up to God in his own will, this would be but Will-worſhip <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45699:6"/> and abomination. This I have known experimentally, and have ſelt the Wrath of God for it. That is Prayer, which comes freſh from the Spirit; and that is a true deſire, which the Spirit begets: but the affections and ſparks of mans kindling pleaſe not the Lord, nor do they conduce to the Souls reſt, but will end in the Bed of ſorrow,
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.11.</p>
            <p>Now as touching the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> or Prayers conceived without the immediate breathings of the Spirit, I ſhall ſpeak mine own experience faithfully, which is this: I have felt both theſe wayes draw out the wrong part, and keep that alive in me, which the true Prayer kills. And he that ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a word, beyond the ſence which God begets in his ſpirit, takes God's Name in vain, and provokes him to jealouſie againſt his own ſoul. <hi>God is in Heaven, thou art on Earth, therefore let thy words be few.</hi> The few words which the Spirit ſpeaks, or the few, ſtill; ſoft, gentle breathings which the Spirit begets, are pleaſing to God, and profitable to the Soul: but the many words, which mans wiſdom affects, hurt the precious life, and thicken the vail of death over the Soul, keeping that part alive, which ſeparates from God; which part muſt dye, e're the Soul can live.</p>
            <p>The true Prayer is by that which God begets, in the vertue of his Spirit (<hi>praying alwayes in the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 6.18. Jude 20.) in the time he chuſes: for the Spirit breatheth as well when he liſteth, as where he liſteth; and man cannot limit him when he ſhall breath, or when he ſhall not breath, but is to wait the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his breathing, and ſo to <hi>watch unto Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Prayer be in words (for there is a praying without words) then it muſt be in thoſe words which he pleaſeth to give, from the ſence which he kindleth, and not in the words which mans wiſdom teacheth, or would chuſe to uſe. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in the true Religion, and in every exerciſe of it, mans wiſdom is kept out, and nail'd to the Croſs, by which means the immortal life is raiſed and grows in the true Diſciple. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, he hopes, he waits, he prayes, he mourns, he rejoyces, he obeyes, &amp;c. in the Croſs to the mortal part: not as mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom teacheth, or would teach, or can teach any of theſe things; for his Sacrifice is ſtill an abomination, even to the wiſe <hi>Egyptian</hi> 
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45699:6"/> part in himſelf (O wiſe man, abaſe thy ſelf before the Lord in his Spirit, that thou mayeſt read this and live) but as the life teacheth, as the Wiſdom from above teacheth, which breaketh down, ſhutteth up, confoundeth and deſtroyeth mans wiſdom, while he is teaching his Babe.</p>
            <p>Thus have I anſwered, in the ſimplicity of my heart, to the nature of the thing, ſo far as the Lord hath pleaſed to draw forth my ſpirit; and in ſinking down to that, which thus opened my ſpirit, my Anſwer may eaſily be read and aſſented to: but to that which is in the diſputing wiſdom, out of the feeling of the hidden life and vertue, it may prove a Myſtery.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, he alſo intreateth me to peruſe ſeriouſly, and to lay deeply to heart (in the real fear and dread of the great God) ſome particulars which he teacheth for Truths.</p>
            <p>I perceive he is offended at the queſtioning of his Miniſtry, and that the main intent of his propoſing theſe, is to juſtifie his Miniſtry; which if they were true, yet the preaching of them would not prove him, or any man elſe, to be a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt: for it is not preaching things that are true, which makes a true Miniſter, but the receiving of his Miniſtry from the Lord. The Goſpel is the Lords, which is to be preached, and it is to be preached in his Power; and the Miniſters which preach it, are to be endued with his Power, and to be ſent by him. The Apoſtles themſelves, though they had received inſtructions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Kingdom from Chriſts own lips, both in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and after his Reſurrection (<hi>Act.</hi> 1.3.) and had received a Commiſſion from him to teach all Nations, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19. Yet this was not ſufficient to make them able Miniſters of the New Teſtament; but before they went abroad to Preach, they were to wait for the Power, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.4, 8. And when they had received it, they were to miniſter in it, that men might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Power and by the Power, that the Faith of perſons might not ſtand in the wiſdom of their words (which <hi>Paul</hi> might have abounded in, as well as others) <hi>but in the Power of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.5. And this was it made <hi>Paul</hi> miniſter in fear and trembling,, leſt the wrong part in him ſhould miniſter, leſt the earthly underſtanding part ſhould be holding forth the Truths of God out of the Life, out of the Power; and ſo he ſhould <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45699:7"/> Convert men to the Wiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m of the words he ſpake, and not to the Power, v. 2, 3. This was it he was ſent for, to turn men <hi>from darkneſs to light, from the Power of Satan to God</hi> (Acts 26.18.) from the ſpirit of enmity and death to the Spirit of Love and Life: and this he was careful of in his Miniſtry, that men might not run away with his words and miſs of the thing. And this alſo was the way whereby he diſcovered true and falſe Miniſters, <hi>I will come and know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not the ſpeech of them which are puffed up, but the Power: for the Kingdom of God is not in word, but in Power,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.19, 20. Many men might catch their words, and run away with them and Preach them, but they could not Miniſter in the Power. Now the Kingdome, which the Goſpel-Miniſters are the Preachers of, conſiſts not in words, but in Power. <hi>God hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit,</hi>
2 Cor. 3.6. The Miniſtry of the New Teſtament is a Miniſtry of the Spirit, and it cannot be without the Spirit. It is a reaching to men's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences <hi>in the demonſtration of the Spirit and of Power</hi> (1 Cor. 2.4. and 2 Cor. 4.1, 2.) which being felt in the heart and turned to, this converts them to God.</p>
            <p>The Miniſtry of the Goſpel doth not conſiſt in a bare opening of the Letter (or raiſing of Doctrines and Uſes from the Letter, which the wiſdom of man may eaſily perform) as the Miniſtry of the Law did: but in bringing men to the feeling of the Spirit, even of the Eternal Power of God which redeems, in turning men from the darkneſs to the Light, in ſetting their faces towards the Power. The Goſpel is the ſubſtance of what was ſhadowed out in the Law; and he that Miniſters it, muſt Miniſter ſubſtance. He muſt have the <hi>heavenly Treaſure</hi> (that's the ſubſtance) in his earthen veſſel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. and he muſt give out of this Treaſure into the veſſel which God prepares: and that he may do this, he muſt Miniſter in the Spirit and in the Power. His words muſt not be ſuch as mans wiſdom would teach, or as mans comprehenſion would gather, but ſuch words as Gods Wiſdom prepares for him, and puts into his mouth. He that will be a true Miniſter, muſt receive both his gift, his Miniſtry, and the exerciſe of both from the Lord; and muſt be ſure in his miniſtring to keep in the Power, or he will never
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45699:7"/> win others to the Power: but in keeping in the Power, while he is miniſtring, and ſtanding in the croſs to his own underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and wiſdom, giving forth the truths which the Lord chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to have him ſpeak, in the words which God chuſeth, even in the words which are miniſtred to him by the Power; in thus miniſtring he ſhall ſave both his own Soul and thoſe that hear him, even all who in fear and meekneſs receive the ingrafted Word, which is able to ſave the Soul. For alas, alas, many have received words of Truth, and apprehenſions of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whereby they hope to be ſaved: but how few are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with that Knowledge which ſtands in the Power, which alone converts and keeps alive unto God! O how many Souls are to be anſwered for by them, who take upon them to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors from God, who have fed the Flock with words, with
<hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes which they have made,</hi> and have ruled over them
<hi>with force and cruelty,</hi> but have wanted the love, the tenderneſs, the Light and Power of the true Shepherd! O what will theſe do, when God requires his ſheep at their hands! O that there were an heart to conſider. Ye Shepherds of <hi>England,</hi> little do ye know what is towards you.</p>
            <p>Now for thoſe things themſelves, which he ſaith, he
<hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally endeavours to make known to the ſons of men,</hi> there is a mixture in them; which, if he could ſingly apply himſelf to wait of the Lord, in the meek ſober Spirit, out of the conſultations, wiſdom and confidence of the fleſh, it might pleaſe the Lord to make manifeſt to him.</p>
            <p>The firſt particular of thoſe, which he layes down for Truths, is, <hi>That the good things of this life, honours, riches,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>unleſs we make uſe of them in the ſervice of God, are but vanity, and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit; And in no wiſe any more capable to ſatisfie, or content an immortal Soul, than Lime, and Aſhes, and Cobwebs, and ſuch like traſh are to ſatisfie, and keep in health the bodies of thoſe perſons, who through the depravedneſs of their appetite, deſire to feed on them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt by his Miniſtry, calleth his Diſciples out of the world, up to the Father, out of the honours, riches and what ever elſe is of the world. <hi>How can ye believe, which receive ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45699:8"/> onely?</hi> John 5.44. And the rich man, he bids him
<hi>ſell all and follow him.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith,
<hi>Love not the world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the things that are in the world. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world, the juſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world,</hi> 1 John 2.15, 16. He that will be a Diſciple of Chriſt, muſt travel out of the earthly into the heavenly, leaving all that is of this world behind him, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing nothing as his portion, but him who hath call'd him out of his Countrey, from among his kindred, and from his Father's houſe to another Land, kindred and habitation. So that here they are Pilgrims and Strangers, Sojourners and Paſſengers, unknown to the world and of a ſtrange garb, behaviour and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in it, not enjoying any thing as the world enjoyes, not uſing any thing as the world uſeth, not honouring men or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving honour from men, as the world gives or receives honour, but honouring men in the Lord, and receiving honour from the Lord: and what ever they ſeem to retain of the earthly things, they hold as Stewards under the Lord, not uſing or diſpoſing of them as they think good, but waiting for the diſcovery of the Maſters pleaſure, who is to order, in his Counſel and Wiſdom, all that is his own to his own glory. The Law required a tenth part to be given up to the Lord: the Goſpel requires all; <hi>Soul, Body, Spirit, Goods, good Name,</hi> &amp;c. even that the whole poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be ſold and laid at the Maſters feet: and he that keepeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing back, cannot be a Diſciple, cannot be a Souldier of Chriſt, but muſt needs <hi>entangle himſelf with the affairs of this life.</hi> This is ſound and ſavoury, even the Truth of Jeſus, as it is known and felt in the renewed Spirit: but his Words, if he meaſure them in the pure Light of God, he will perceive not to have ſprung thence, but to have been formed in the earthly wiſe part, even in that wiſdom, underſtanding and comprehenſion, which is ſhut out of the Myſteries of Gods Kingdom.</p>
            <p>For his ſecond, <hi>That nothing but the enjoyment of God, the Fountain of all Goodneſs, can truly and really content an immortal Soul:</hi> And for his third, <hi>That no man can enjoy God, but he that loves him with all his heart, and with all his Soul, and (for his ſake) his Neighbour as himſelf:</hi> I own both the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45699:8"/> and theſe words, and I felt a good ſavour in them at the reading of them: onely let me ſay this, if he put men upon ſtriving after theſe things, without pointing them to the gift where the ſtrength is received to perform, and where the wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to be for the ſtrength, he cannot preach them profitably to his hearers.</p>
            <p>To his fourth, <hi>That, though every ſincere Convert, or regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſon loves God continually with his whole heart, as to the habit, or root of holy love; yet whilſt he is in the body, he may ſometimes fail of the Act, or fruit of it, and may offend God through the love of the creature. Which Truth (ſo much oppoſed in theſe dayes) is clear, and manifeſt in the holy Scriptures: particularly in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the hainous ſins of the Prophet David, and Peter the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Lord <hi>Circumciſeth the heart</hi> of Believers under the New Covenant, <hi>to love the Lord their God with all their heart, that they may live: he cauſeth the Plant to ſpring up out of the dry and barren ground, which he watereth with his Bleſſing; and he layeth his Axe to the Root of the old Tree, hewing at it, even till he hath cut it up: he engrafteth the Eternal Word into the heart, and by it is daily purifying thereof, fulfilling the good pleaſure of his goodneſs therein, and carrying on the Work of Faith with power:</hi> and the Miniſtry which he gave, was for the <hi>perfecting of the Saints.</hi> (Epheſ. 4.12, 13.) which Miniſtry exhorted and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Believers (from God's Promiſes of his preſence and powerful operation of his Spirit in the hearts of his Sons and Daughters) to
<hi>cleanſe themſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1. Now that the corrupt Tree ſhall never be cut down whilſt man is in the body, that the heart ſhall never be throughly circumciſed to love the Lord, but be in danger of
<hi>offending God through the love of the Creature:</hi> this doctrine and belief ſpringeth not from the pure Fountain of Life and Power, but the reaſoning part hath gathered it from it's conceivings beneath the Power.</p>
            <p>The Seed of God cannot ſin (for as he is pure which begetteth, ſo is that pure which is begotten of him) nor can man ſin, who is born of it and abides in it: and if God pleaſe to perfect the Birth and the work of Circumciſion, What can hinder a man <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45699:9"/> from being wholly born of it &amp; from abiding in it? Indeed a man that ſtrives in his own ſtrength, either againſt ſin or towards ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, may well doubt of ever having it accompliſhed: but he that feels the Eternal Power beginning the work, and carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it on daily, cannot doubt but he can perfect it, yea, and is encouraged (by the feeling thereof) to hope and wait on him for the perfecting of it.</p>
            <p>As for his inſtances of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> they reach not the thing: For though <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did fall, yet both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> might attain an higher ſtate before they went out of the body, then they were in before they fell. <hi>David</hi> was a great Prophet, and <hi>Peter</hi> a pretious Diſciple, but yet there was an higher Eſtate to be adminiſtred, even the receiving that which the Prophets propheſied of, and which the Diſciple was to wait for. The Diſciples who had known Chriſt, and had been taught by him, and had received a Commiſſion from him, to whom all Power in Heaven and Earth was given, yet were to wait for a Further and Higher State, even for receiving
<hi>the Promiſe of the Father, the Power from on High,</hi> that he that was with them might be in them, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. <hi>John</hi> was as great as any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and yet he that was leaſt in the Kingdom, was greater then he. Read the Acts of the Apoſtles, behold what a preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people was brought forth, even in the beginning of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Miniſtry, how full of Faith, how ſtripped of the world, how ſingle-hearted to God and one towards another, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>) What would theſe be, abiding and growing up in the Vine? The cutting off of ſin, is neceſſary while in the Body, but to make the committing of ſin neceſſary while in the Body, is a great Derogation to the Power of Gods Grace, and to the <hi>Myſtery of Faith,</hi> which overcometh the evils of the Heart, and the Worldly Nature within; purifieth the Conſcience from dead works, and is <hi>held in the Pure Conſcience.</hi> O that men knew the Power, and the Faith which ſtands in the Power: For then would not they judge it ſo impoſſible to be cleanſed by the Faith through the Power. O that Light, that Light, that Pure Light of the Spirit, wherein the Living Blood runs, which cleanſeth from all ſin, and keepeth clean them that abide and walk in it! If this were but a little felt, ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45699:9"/> as theſe (which are gathered in the comprehenſion from words read, without being let into the thing it ſelf) would ſoon vaniſh, and find no place in the Heart where the Power dwells, nor in the underſtanding which is renewed, preſerved and fed by the Power. For the things of God are to be known, and held in the underſtanding which is given of God (which underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is of the Spirit, and is Spiritual) and not wirh the natural underſtanding, which cannot receive the things of the Spirit, but onely a carnal apprehenſion and ſence of the words of the Spirit, according as a man can beat them out with, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them in his reaſoning part.</p>
            <p>To the fifth, <hi>That the Souls of the faithful are alwayes growing in grace, whilſt they are in the body; and at the inſtant of death, or ſeparation from the body, our Lord Jeſus ſhall preſent them to the Father without ſpot, or blemiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt preſenteth to the Father, when he hath purified the heart and mind, and made it fit for Gods pure life and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. He hath received the fulneſs from the Father, and hath freely given of his grace and of his truth to the ſons of men, to regenerate them, to cleanſe and ſanctifie their hearts, and make them fit for God to dwell in. He ſitteth in his Temple as <hi>a Refiner and Purifier of Silver</hi> (who is like <hi>a Refiner's Fire and like Fuller's Soap</hi>) and when he hath purified his Diſciples, his Children, his Levites, he preſenteth them to the Lord, for the Lord to Tabernacle and dwell in: when he hath throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated them, he preſenteth them as Kings and Prieſts to his Father, to offer up <hi>an Offering for Righteouſneſs,</hi> and to reign with him in his Kingdom, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. And there were ſome ſo purified by the leaven of the Kingdom (which purgeth out the old leaven by degrees, even till at length it hath made the lump wholly new) that to them all things were pure, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5. There were ſome <hi>come unto Mount Sion, and unto the City of the living God, the heavenly Jeruſalem, and to an innumerable company of Angels, to the general Aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born, which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the Spirits of juſt men, made perfect, and to Jeſus the Moderator of the New Covenant, and to the Blood of Sprinkling,</hi> Heb. 12.22, 23, 24. Thus it was before the Apoſtacy: yea, <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45699:10"/> and after the Apoſtacy there were ſome found ſtanding on <hi>Mount Sion</hi> again, ſuch as had learned the <hi>New Song,</hi> ſuch as <hi>were redeemed from the Earth,</hi> ſuch as <hi>were not defiled with Women,</hi> (with any of the falſe Churches or their falſe wayes of worſhip) but had kept their Virginity in the Wilderneſs. If ye would know who theſe were, they were the
<hi>firſt-fruits unto God and the Lamb</hi> after the Apoſtacy, who were throughly cleanſed by the Spirit of burning, inſomuch as <hi>in their mouth was found no guile,</hi> but <hi>they were without fault before the Throne of God,</hi> Revel. 14. v. 1. to 6.</p>
            <p>The Work of the Spirit of Chriſt in the heart is an inward work, and doth not conſiſt in outward time or ſeaſons, but in ſpiritual degrees and ſeaſons: which when they are finiſhed, the heart renewed, the ſpirit changed, the work wrought out; then the glory of the Father is revealed, the entrance into the everlaſting Kingdom Miniſtred, and then there is a ſitting down in the everlaſting Manſion, even with Chriſt in the Heavenly places which he hath prepared, where they that are redeemed, and purged, and ſanctified, ſit together with him: and as the body cannot hinder his entring into the ſpirits of his Saints, and his dwelling in them, no more can it hinder their entring into him and dwelling in him.</p>
            <p>Now there are ſeveral exerciſes of Spirit, ſeveral meaſures of Faith, and ſeveral degrees of Life and Glory. Some are under the Clouds, ſome in the Sea; ſome in <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſome in the Wilderneſs; ſome waiting for his appearance, ſome in the enjoyment of him already appeared. In ſome the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, of Sanctification, of newneſs of Spirit and Life is but begun, in others it is interrupted and they come to a loſſe; in ſome it is much carried on, even towards conſummation, and ſome are already <hi>compleat in him,</hi> finding fulneſs of ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in him (in whom the everlaſting Springs are opened, to the full content of their hearts) and bring forth fruit to him, to the full content and ſatisfaction of his heart. In the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes there were thoſe that waited for his coming, and there were thoſe alſo that knew him come, and had received the good underſtanding from him, and were <hi>in the Eternal life,</hi> John 5.20.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45699:10"/>Yet this doth not exclude growth, for the fulneſs is infinite: and though a perfect ſtate may be attained in the perfect gift, yet there is a growth in the perfection (for Chriſt who was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and in whom was no guile, grew in Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and in favour with God and men.) And as God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, ſo that which is tranſplanted into him, there is no growth in him; but the Tree, which ſtands in God's holy Earth, by his pure River of waters, ſhall grow for ever into his endleſs life and fulneſs.</p>
            <p>To his ſixth, <hi>That no man can ſo know God as to love him with all his heart, and with all his Soul, but through the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and him Crucified: Who, by thoſe grievous ſufferings which he endur'd when he was upon Earth, made ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God for the ſins of all thoſe that believe in his Name: ſo that it is as conſiſtent with the juſtice, as with the mercy of God, to forgive them their ſins, and make them heirs of eternal life. God is juſt, and the Juſtifier of him that believeth in Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The knowledge of Chriſt is life Eternal, and in his Croſs is the ſpiritual vertue, which cuts off the uncircumciſion of the heart, whereby it is enabled to love the Lord. Now <hi>Chriſt</hi> is
<hi>the Lord from Heaven, the quickning Spirit,</hi> who ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Seed of the Kingdom in the heart, and cauſeth it to ſpring up; out of which Seed the Faith, the Love, the Hope, the Meekneſs, the Patience, and every ſpiritual fruit ſprings and grows. And he that is thus born of this Seed, and receives the knowledge of life which ſprings from this Seed, he cannot but love him which begat him, and he reapeth the fruit of all that Chriſt did and ſuffered in that prepared body: and God is both juſt, and the Juſtifier of him, who is thus united to Jeſus. But that man who knoweth not this Faith, nor is acquainted with the love which ſpringeth from this Root, and which is of this Divine nature, but thinketh to be juſtified by applying to himſelf what is related in the Hiſtories concerning Chriſt; this man deceives his Soul, and miſſeth of the true Juſtification: for God is juſt, who hath made the Promiſe ſure to the Seed, and hath ſhut out man, further than he is born of the Seed, and found in the Seed. But he who abideth in the Seed, and in whom the Seed findeth pleaſure and abideth, he cannot miſs of <pb n="18" facs="tcp:45699:11"/> the Promiſe, of the everlaſting Righteouſneſs, the Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Peace, the Joy, and whatever elſe God giveth to the Seed.</p>
            <p>To his ſeventh and laſt, <hi>That the ready way to receive Chriſt, the onely Light, by which we may ſee the way to Heaven: or ſo to believe in him that we may be ſaved by him, is, to forſake all that we have, that we may be his Diſciples: that is to ſay, to take off our affections from things on the Earth, and to ſet them on things above, where Jeſus ſitteth on the right hand of God: putting our truſt and confidence in the free, and in the infinite mercy of God, through Chriſt, to be guided by him in all our wayes, to be led by his good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in all thoſe wayes of grace and holineſs, through which we muſt paſs before we can attain to glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To know Chriſt as the Light eternal, (as he was yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, is to day, and will be for ever) to truſt this Light in its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, calls, and free openings of love, to feel its living vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and in that virtue to give up all thats of the earthly nature and ſpirit, to ſell it for the everlaſting inheritance, this is indeed the way to life. But it is not the doing of things which is of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, for man may imitate and ſtrive to do much, and may go a great way <hi>in forſaking all, and in taking off his affections from things,</hi> (inaſmuch as he may give all his goods to the poor, and his body to be burned, and yet it profit him nothing:) but it is the doing of things in the virtue, in the life, in the power which comes from Chriſt, which is of acceptance with God, and of advantage to the ſoul. Every motion and operation of true life ſprings from the root of life, and hath the virtue of the root in it: and that which differenceth it from all mens imitations, and from all the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which the earthly ſpirit can frame, is the nature and virtue of the root being found in it. Therefore he that will be a true Chriſtian, muſt eye Chriſt the ſpring of his life, and keep in the feeling of his living virtue, and in that offer up all his Sacrifices of faith, love, and obedience to God: and he that will be a true Miniſter, muſt wait upon the power himſelf, to be an Inſtrument (in the hand of the power) to direct men to this, and to preſerve and build them up therein.</p>
            <p>But alas, this is the Stone, which the wiſe Builders have all along refuſed! The Builders before the coming of Chriſt, they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45699:11"/> got a knowledge concerning the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> to come, but being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with the thing it ſelf, rejected both it at its coming, and alſo the Veſſel wherein it appeared. And the Builders all along the Apoſtacy, gat a knowledge of Chriſt come, and preached Believing in him crucified as the way to life; but the living Stone, the living thing it ſelf (which is both the foundation, the corner-Stone, and the top Stone of the Building) they have been ignorant of, and ready to perſecute every appearance of it. Chriſt can no more now appear in Spirit, than formerly he could in that prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red body of fleſh; but the wiſe Builders now are as ready to cry out againſt him for a Blaſphemer, a prophaner of Gods Ordinances, a deceiver of the people (yea, a Witch or one that hath a Devil) as the wiſe Builders then were. <hi>But Wiſdom</hi> in all ages <hi>is juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by her Children,</hi> and of none elſe. He that is born of the Wiſdom, he can diſcern the womb, and own the fruit and branchings forth thereof under the mean dark vail, whereby it hides it ſelf from all the fleſhly wiſe of every age. <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God cometh not by obſervation,</hi> the wiſeſt Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees could not know it by all the obſervations, which they could gather out of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets Writings; nor can any now know it, by any obſervations they can gather out of the Apoſtles Writings: but by being born of that ſpirit whereof they were born, and by being formed in that womb wherein they were formed, by this means alone is the thing come to be known which they knew. He that receiveth the ſame eye, ſeeth the ſame thing, according to his meaſure: and coming to the life, wherein they received the Truth, the words which they ſpake concerning the Truth are eaſie. Thus as they were writ in the Spirit, ſo are they there along truly read: and being ſo read, they become exceeding profitable to that which ſo reads them: but man gueſſing, and imagining, and reaſoning in his carnal wiſdom concerning the things of God, and ſo gathering ſences and meanings about the words and expreſſions of Scripture, doth but build up a <hi>Babel,</hi> which the eternal Life and Power will throw down (when ever he appears) with that which built it. O that men were wiſe to wait for the diſcovery of the true Rock, and of the true Builder upon that Rock, that that City and Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding might be raiſed in them, which God alone can rear, that <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45699:12"/> they might not be left deſolate and miſerable in that ſtormy day, which will ſhake all Buildings, and Foundations, and Rocks but our Rock: wherein all Profeſſors, and Preachers, and high Notioniſts, and what ever ſort elſe can be named (who have ſtumbled at Gods living Truth, and at the pure appearance of his redeeming Power, which in this age hath mightily broke forth, after the long dark night of Apoſtacy, to the ſight of every eye which is opened in the Spirit) ſhall confeſs with tears, ſorrow, anguiſh and ſhame, that <hi>their Rock is not in our Rock, they themſelves being Judges.</hi> For though all ſort of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors generally own Chriſt as the Rock in words, yet moſt miſs of the thing: and the ſubtile Enemy hath made uſe of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or apprehenſion of the thing in the carnal mind, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them of the thing, to keep them from feeling the eternal vertue, the living Power of Life in the heart, which is the Arm of Gods Salvation, whereby Chriſt draws mans loſt ſoul and ſpirit out of the Pit, out of the Grave, out of Sin and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption up to the Father. But O how are poor hearts deceived, who think by a believing of what Chriſt did, of a ſatisfaction he made for them while he was here on Earth, though they lye in the Pit all their dayes, though they carry the body of ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with them to the very laſt of their time here in the body, and have not felt the Arm of God's Power breaking down their ſpiritual enemies, their luſts, their corruptions, and redeeming them from them, yet hope to be ſaved in the end, and to be preſented without ſpot or wrinkle to God! Chriſt had the name
<hi>Jeſus</hi> given him, becauſe he was to ſave his People from their ſin: and no man can truly and livingly know the name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> further than he feels the ſaving vertue of it: but he that effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually feels the vertue, he indeed knows the name, and can bow at the name, feeling his luſts and enemies bowed under by the power thereof, and that raiſed up in him, which can Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Father in the Spirit and in the Truth. O that the ſons of men knew, O that the Teachers and Profeſſors of this age knew, what they have ſo long reviled and trampled upon! Surely they would mourn bitterly, kiſs the Son, and eſcape the wrath.</p>
            <p>Now, if the Lord pleaſe to ſmite any ones earthly wiſdom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45699:12"/> and comprehenſion (which is the main thing which ſtands in the way of the pure openings and revelations of the life) and give him the feeling of any thing here written, let him in fear acknowledge the Lord, ſacrificing to his goodneſs, and waiting upon him to be kept in that feeling, not magnifying or villifying any of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, but in meekneſs and humility embracing the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Almighty, from the hand which he pleaſeth to give them forth by. As for me, I am but a Shell; and if this party knew me (who ſets me up ſo high, preferring me above many, whom the Lord hath preferred far above me) he would ſoon acknowledge me to be a very poor, weak, contemptible one: yet this I muſt by no means deny, that the pure Liquor of the eternal Life, at its pleaſure ſpringeth up and iſſueth out through me; though I can alſo in true underſtanding ſay, that it iſſueth out far oftener and much more abundantly through others. Let it have its honour, where ever it appears; and the Lord bring down that in peoples hearts, which hindreth the owning and receiving of its virtue.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Warning of tender Bowels to the Rulers, Teachers, and People of the Nation, concerning their <hi>Church</hi> and
<hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat there was a Fight between the Dragon and his Angels, and
<hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, concerning the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Church and Miniſtry, is manifeſt even from the Letter of the Scriptures, <hi>Rev.</hi>
12.</p>
               <p>That the Dragon and his Angels, though they could not get the better, as relating to the Power, yet that they did get the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as relating to the Form, inſomuch as that they overcame the third part of the true Miniſters, and drew them from their ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Firmament of Gods Power, off to their earthly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and that the Church her ſelf alſo was fain to fly into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, from the face of the Dragon, for her ſafety and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where ſhe was to be nouriſhed and ſed by God all the time of Antichriſts Reign; this likewiſe is not onely revealed in the <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45699:13"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45699:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:45699:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45699:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45699:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:45699:15"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:45699:16"/> Spirit, but is alſo manifeſt from the Letter,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>That after this flight of the true Church and overcoming of the true Miniſtry, the Dragon erected his falſe Church and Miniſtry (which had but at beſt the Form without the Power) over all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Peoples, Multitudes and Tongues, this is alſo as evident, to them that read the Prophecies of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> in the Light of that Spirit that wrote them. Is nor the falſe woman (after the true woman was fled) manifeſtly deſcribed? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. which hath a bewitching Cup of Fornications,
<hi>v.</hi> 2, and 4. Mark, She hath not the true <hi>Cup of Bleſſing,</hi> her cup is not filled with the <hi>Wine of the Kingdom,</hi> it is not the Cup of the true Spouſe, (which keeps chaſt and loyal to the bed of the Husband) but the cup of Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, wherein is a Form of Doctrine, and Diſcipline, and Order, and Church-Government which leads from the life, which be witneſſes from the Power, which luls aſleep in a Form of profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and worſhip of Chriſt, without knowledge of, guidnace by, and ſubjection to his Spirit. And this is the Government, Miniſtry, and way of Antichriſt, where ever it is found: how curiouſly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the cup be guilded, yet it is but the cup of Fornication, which bewitcheth the heart with its golden appearance, and then leads it into adultery from the life. And the Dragon doth not onely ſet up a falſe Church over the Nations (in many parts whereof the truth had before appeared) <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15. but a falſe Miniſtry alſo. There's a falſe Prophet (which deceiveth with Miracles and falſe appearances of truth) advanced in this corrupt ſtate: which falſe Prophet continues and upholds his deceit over the Nations, till the mighty appearance of Chriſt in Spirit and Power, do judge him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. 2
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. There's a Beaſt with <hi>Horns like a Lamb,</hi> who
<hi>doth great Wonders, ſo that he maketh Fire come down from Heaven on the Earth, in the ſight of men, and deceiveth them that dwell on the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.13, 14. Inſomuch as he drawes the Kings and Inhabiters of the Earth (in a Myſterie of deceit) into the Bed of Whoredom and falſe Worſhip, inſtead of the pure way of Life, and pure Worſhip of the living God, in his Spirit, and in his truth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2.</p>
               <p>Is it not further manifeſt, that this falſe Church and falſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, ſet up in the World by the power of the Dragon, perſecute Gods Witneſſes to the truth, in all the ages of Antichriſts reign? <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45699:16"/> So ſoon as ere the Church was fled into the Wilderneſs, the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon forthwith went to <hi>make War with the remnant of her ſeed, which kept the Commandments of God, and had the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rev. 12.17. <hi>And it was given unto him to make War with the Saints, and to overcome them: and power was given him over all Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, Tongues, and Nations. And all that dwell upon the earth ſhall worſhip him, whoſe names are not written in the Book of Life of the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the World. If any man have an ear let him hear,</hi> Rev. 13.7, 8, 9. <hi>And he had power to give life unto the Image of the Beaſt, that the Image of the Beaſt ſhould both ſpeak, and cauſe that as many as would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, ſhould be killed. And he cauſeth all, both ſmall and great, rich and poor, free and bond, to receive a Mark in their right hand, or in their fore-heads. And that no man might buy or ſell ſave he that had the Mark, or the name of the Beaſt, or the number of his Name,</hi> Rev. 13.15, 16, 17. Yea, <hi>the Woman</hi> (the falſe Church, which the Dragon had ſet up, by his power in the Nations, inſtead of the true) was <hi>drunken with the Blood of the Saints, and with the Blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 17.6. O the miſery, and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hard uſage of the Witneſſes of Jeſus, who have been true Lambs, born of the Power, faithful to the Power, witneſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every Form and appearance of Religion, Doctrine and Worſhip, which hath appeared without the Power (even in the daies of greateſt profeſſion and higheſt devotion under the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy from the Power) how have theſe been hunted, perſecuted, devoured by the Wolves in the Sheeps cloathing, who had got the outſide, the garment, the Name of Chriſt and Chriſtianity, the profeſſion of Church, Miniſtry, and Ordinances, but have want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the life, the virtue, the thing it ſelf; and ſo have turned againſt it, and kept it down, that they might keep up their Form! For let but the Power appear, the Form without the Power is ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected to be what it is. And this is properly Antichriſt and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme, to wit, Not openly to appear in a direct denyal of Chriſt, his Truths and Worſhip, but to ſet up a way of knowledge and worſhip without his Spirit. Another ſpirit creeping into the Form, that's Antichriſt (and the ſetting up obſervation and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Form out of the Life and Power, that's Antichriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme) and this is the perſecuter, deſtroyer, and devourer about Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45699:17"/>Now though the Lord hath ſuffered this falſe Church, and falſe Prophet to reign long in the Dragons power, and to revile and worry his poor Lambs, in every age of Antichriſts Reign; yet the Lord hath appointed a ſeaſon to judge this falſe Church, <hi>Rev.</hi>
17.1. to caſt the falſe Prophet into the Lake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.
<hi>v.</hi> 20. yea and to torment with fire and brimſtone, all the falſe Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p>O how deeply doth it concern <hi>England,</hi> her Rulers, her Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, yea the whole People thereof, to conſider their Ways, to conſider their Worſhip, to conſider their Church-ſtate, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their Miniſtry, that they be not overwhelmed at unawars in the bitter wrath of the Almighty, before which there is no ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. O that they could mourn, and pray, and wait for the eye of Gods Spirit, for his pure Light, which ſearcheth and diſcovereth all the deceits of Antichriſt; that they might not be bewitched with any of the wine of the fornication of the falſe Woman,
<hi>whoſe heart is ſnares and nets, and her hands as bands,</hi> to entangle her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in, and keep them from the pure bed of Life, where the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Life, with the Son and Spirit, are enjoyed and worſhipped.</p>
               <p>If men conſult concerning theſe things in the wiſdom of the fleſh, they will be entangled and erre; for that eye cannot ſee the Myſteries of the Kingdom, or the courſe either of Truth or Deceit. The Goſpel, the Eternal Truth, the true Church, the true Miniſtry, are all Spiritual, (not new ſhadowes, as the things under the miniſtration of the Law were, but Spirit and Subſtance) and they can onely be ſeen by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual eye of the children of Wiſdom. The wiſe Hunters, and diligent Enquirers, into the comprehending part, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find the Womb or the way of Life, or the way of the Worſhip of that which is begotten in the Life, or Gods way of Miniſtry, which he hath appointed for the feeding and preſerving of the Life. The Prophets of old could not be known, diſcerned, or own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the fleſhly eye of obſervation in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after the fleſh, (but they ſtill rejected them, eſteeming and magnifying the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets above them) how much leſs can the Prophets and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the New Teſtament be ſeen by mans eye? Are they the Prophets and Miniſters of Chriſt, which a Nation cries up for ſuch, and which the eye of the wiſe men therein admires, and <pb n="25" facs="tcp:45699:17"/> pitches upon? or, are thoſe they which the renewed eye, in the Light of the Lord ſees to be fitted, ſanctified and called forth by Chriſt unto that ſervice? Ah poor
<hi>England,</hi> muſt thou fall into the pit before thine eyes be opened!</p>
               <p>The great Controverſie of this Age is about Church and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, which muſt carry it, the Form or the Power; Whether the Church and Miniſtry, ſhall take place which was before the Apoſtacy, or that which hath ſprung up in or ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy? Whether mans wiſdom ſhall determine which is the true Church and its true Miniſtry, or whether the Spirit of God ſhall determine it? Whether a Nation, with the Miniſters it ſets up, ſhall be the Church and Miniſtry? or whether Gods holy Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which he calleth and ſanctifieth by his Spirit) and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters which he chuſeth, and ſendeth to gather and build up his in the holy Faith and pure power of Life, ſhall be the Church and Miniſtry? Our eyes wait on the Lord to ſee this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie determined, and our hope of help is in his Arm, nor are we at all affrighted at the riſing of any ſtrength againſt us (our hearts being given up to Gods Truth, and to ſuffer for its Teſtimony, according to Gods will, meekly and patiently in his ſtrength) but we pitty this poor land, yea in the depth of bowels we pitty the Rulers, the Teachers and People therein. O that they might be humbled, and in fear of the great God, ſurrender to him his due, before he appear in his ſtrength to force it from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Kingdom, Laws, and Government of Chriſt in the Heart and Conſcience, its Inoffenſiveneſs to all juſt Laws and Governments of the Kingdoms of men.</head>
               <p>CHriſts Kingdom, Gods Kingdom, the Kingdom of Heaven (for they are all one and the ſame) is that ſeed of Eternal Life, which God hath hid in the hearts of the ſons of men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he gathereth them back unto himſelf, bringeth them under the Yoak of his Government, ruleth over them, and reigneth in them.</p>
               <p>This Kingdom is likened to <hi>a grain of muſtard ſeed,</hi> for its ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <pb n="26" facs="tcp:45699:18"/> to <hi>a Pearl,</hi> for its Riches, Value and Worth; to <hi>Leaven,</hi> for its ſpreading nature: and many other Parables did Chriſt make uſe of to diſcover it by, as to <hi>a piece of Silver,</hi> which the woman that loſt it, lighting the candle, ſweeping the houſe and ſearching it diligently, at length found it even there where ſhe had loſt it.</p>
               <p>Man fallen from God, is become loſt as to the Lord, and as to his own happineſs in the Lord, being driven from his bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and divine Image, Life and Spirit, into the earthly Spirit, Image and Life which he choſe. Yet in this Earth, in this Field of the World God hath hid ſomewhat, even the everlaſting Pearl; which when man is awakened to ſeek, and findeth in the living Breath, in the Eternal Light of Life; it is able to redeem him, it is able to overſpread, (he becoming ſubject to the Laws, Leadings, Teachings and Power of it) and leaven him into the Likeneſs and Image of the pure Life and Spirit.</p>
               <p>Or not men knew the Gift of God, O that men knew the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of the blood of Chriſt, O that men knew that Spiritual good thing, which Chriſt (who died for them) hath given to Redeem them by, that in that they might be united to Chriſt, and ſo by him be Renewed and Reſtored to God. For as the Father recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth none but through the Son; ſo the Son receiveth none but in that Gift, which he beſtoweth from the Father. He owneth no Faith, no Love, no Hope, no Repentance, no Obedience, but what ſpringeth from that, and ſtandeth in that.</p>
               <p>Now as man is Born of this, is Leavened by this, (as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a fool in his own earthly wiſdom and excellency of the fallen Spirit, and becomes a Babe, a Child, Simple, Innocent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſo he enters into the Kingdome, being ingrafted into the Root through the virtue of this which is given him from the Root, and ſo grows up in this, and this in him. And here's the new Nature, the new Life, the new Heart, the new Spirit, in which the Unity and Fellowſhip with God is again known, and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union with the World, the Wiſdom, the Intereſts, the Faſhions, the Cuſtoms, the Fears, the Hopes, the Delights, the Joys, of this World and whatever elſe is of it. For Chriſt, as he is not of the World, ſo he calleth men out of the World; and they which follow him, and become his Diſciples, go out of the World after him; that is, travel in Spirit and Converſation from what is of the Earth, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45699:18"/> from what ever is <hi>not of the Father, but of the World. They are not of the World, even as I am not of the World</hi> (ſaith Chriſt concerning his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>therefore the world hateth them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Laws of this Kingdom are given forth in the Kingdom, from the Covenant of life, which is made there in Chriſt. They are written in the heart, in the mind, as far as it is renewed. There the <hi>fear</hi> is put, there the <hi>eternal Wiſdom</hi> is opened, there is <hi>Sion</hi> known, and the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which is from above, and the <hi>Laws</hi> of eternal life iſſue freſh from it, and are revealed by the life, in the heart which is turned towards the life. There ſin is reproved, and everlaſting Righteouſneſs manifeſted, in the Light which cannot deceive: and as the heart is made ſubject under the yoke, ſo ſin is wrought out and Righteouſneſs brought in; and under the Croſs, or yoke of life, the blood of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Covenant runs through the veſſel, to keep it pure, ſweet, clean and freſh in the life.</p>
               <p>This then is the Government of Chriſt, to be ſubject to his Spirit, which appears and opens his will, in the gift of grace which comes from him; to feel his living breath, by which the heart is begotten to God, out of the Region of darkneſs; to know the movings, the ſtirrings, the leadings, the ſteps of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> who is <hi>the Captain of our Salvation;</hi> and to follow him where ever he goes, doing all things that he commands, forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things that he forbids, <hi>without murmuring, without diſputing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who ever will be of the inward <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which Chriſt redeems out of the ſpiritual
<hi>Egypt,</hi> and leads through the ſpiritual Wilderneſs into the Land of Reſt, muſt know his Leader, muſt receive his Spirit, and follow it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> he is none of the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and if any man follow not the Spirit of Chriſt, through all the travels in the Wilderneſs, (but either ſits down by the way, or lyes overcome by any kind of enemies, and comes not to the end of his journey, finiſhing the warfar and fight of Faith) he falls ſhort of the reſt. O that men were awakened to conſider of things as indeed they are: for Religion is not ſuch an outward Form of Doctrine, or Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of any ſort, as men generally (whoſe poor Souls are decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through the ſubtilty of the powers of darkneſs) are too apt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45699:19"/> and willing to apprehend; but it conſiſts in Spirit, in Power, in Vertue, in Life: not in the oldneſs of any Form which paſſeth away, but in the newneſs of the Spirit, which abideth for ever; in being born of the Spirit, in abiding in the Spirit, in living, walking and worſhipping in the Spirit, yea, in beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and growing into Spirit, and into eternal Life: for <hi>that which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit.</hi> O that the ſons of men would hearken, that they might taſt of the ſweetneſs and riches of the goodneſs, which the Father in his free love hath opened in the ſpirits of many, and hath let the ſpirits of many into. O that men would ſuffer the wearing out of this earthly ſpirit and wiſdom, that they might become like God, be formed into and live in his Image. How long ſhall the Deſtroyer in every age, prejudice men againſt them in that age, which ſeek their good with their hearts! How long will the world ſtand in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the generation of God's choice, and provoke the Lord to wrath againſt them! Surely the ſpirit of this world will try it out to the very laſt againſt the Spirit of God: for indeed, the ſpirit of this world is not ſubject to the Spirit of God, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can be, and ſo cannot endure the Government of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (which is not of this world) to be ſet up in the ſight of it.</p>
               <p>Yet the Government of Chriſt and his Kingdom, is not oppoſite to any juſt Government of a Nation or People. Chriſt's Government is a Righteous Government of the heart, or inner man chiefly, which doth not oppoſe a Righteous Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the outward man. Nay, thoſe who are Chriſt's ſubjects, and ſingly obedient to his Law of Righteouſneſs in their ſpirits; are more faithful to men, and more ſubject to any juſt Law of Government, than others can be: for their fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſubjection is out of love, and for Conſcience ſake. But this is it which offends the world, men many times make Laws in their own will, and according to their own wiſdom (now the wiſdom of the world is corrupt, and hath erred from the guide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God) and are not free from ſelf-ends and intereſts, not being gathered into that, which cleanſeth and keepeth pure the naturals. Now that which is of God, cannot bow to any thing which is corrupt in man: it can lye down and ſuffer, and bear the plowing of long and deep ſurrows upon its back, but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <pb n="29" facs="tcp:45699:19"/> act that which is againſt its life. It cannot be diſloyal to its King, to gratifie the ſpirit of this world; but what Practice or Teſtimony its King calls for, againſt the evil and corruption of this world, it muſt obey ſingly and faithfully.</p>
               <p>God in every age ſo bringeth forth and ordereth his innocent Lambs and People, as that they are ſtill offenſive to the preſent age. The Lord fitteth them, and calleth them forth to be Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt the evils of the preſent age, How can they but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it? Can darkneſs chuſe but hate the light, which ſpeaks againſt it? How can darkneſs in Power and Dominion, bear to be reproved by a mean contemptible appearance of the Light, in mean and contemptible veſſels? For God chuſeth <hi>the weak, and fooliſh things of this world, and things that are not, to bring to nought things that are.</hi> Look into former ages, How did God reprove the Kings and Princes of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Not by the eminent Prieſts and Prophets, whom they expected to be taught by, but by Herdſmen, by Plowmen, by Prophets which they deſpiſed. How did he overcome the Heatheniſh world, yea, and the Jewiſh corrupted ſtate? Was it by wiſe learned men (by the learned Scribes and Phariſees among the Jews, or by the wiſe Grecians among the Heathen) or by Fiſhermen and Publicans? And how ſhall the recovery out of the Apoſtacy, and the reproof of the Antichriſtian world be? Shall it be by wiſe Synods and Councils of learned and Orthodox men among them (as they ſpeak?) Or ſhall it be by the learning of the ſpirit in ſuch as theſe contemn? When God hath the rich Treaſure of the Knowledge of his Kingdom to manifeſt in the world, he chuſes earthen veſſels, weak veſſels, poor contemptible perſons (he appears there, where the eye of man leaſt look for him) that <hi>the excellency of the Power</hi> might appear to be of him wholly, and that the veſſel might rob him of none of the glory of it. Now the Lord hath not only choſen, in this day of his great appearance in Spirit to the ſpirits of his People, mean inſtruments, but mean things alſo, fooliſh things, weak things, the keeping on of an Hat, the uſe of ordinary Language, the appearing in mean habits and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed geſtures, yea, and in a fooliſh way of Preaching (indeed it is ſo, to that which hath not the ſavour of the Vertue and Power of the life in it) And how can the wiſdom of man but ſtumble <pb n="30" facs="tcp:45699:20"/> at it? Who would think that God ſhould require ſuch things, or appear in ſuch thirds? O living eternal Power, how is thy migthy Preſence and Appearance vailed from all, that look for it in any way of mans obſervation, or judge it with the eye of mans wiſdom! <hi>Verily, thou art a God that haſt hid thy ſelf from the earthly ſpirit in its utmoſt wiſdom, yea, in its utmoſt ſearch after the knowledge of, and in the midſt of the higheſt porfeſſion of Religion!</hi> Which of the Wiſe, which of the Scribes in this Age can diſcern any of thy Pathes, or ſo much as one of thy Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps! Oh that men would fear before the Lord, and be ſure to Govern in that which is of God, and then they ſhould harm none of His, nor hazard the ſhaking of their Government: but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not of God, both within and without, muſt fall in the day of Gods Power. O happy is he, who is now made willing to part with that, which God is determined to rent from man, that his ſtanding may be in that which cannot be ſhaken. For there hath been a great Earthquake in this Nation, both of things without and of things within; and there yet remains ſomewhat to be ſhaken both without and within, that the Glory of God may have room to appear. O <hi>England, Kiſs the Son leſt he be angry:</hi> Let all ſuch Laws and Cuſtoms as are not of Him, fall before Him, and whatever is of Him, let it bow unto Him (both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out) that his wrath break not forth like a fire, which none can quench. For the Lord hath mighty things to bring to paſs, and he hath a mighty Arm of Power to effect them by, and what ſhall be able to ſtand before him, that ſtands in his way?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults in Printing.</head>
            <p>Page 11. line 23. for, <hi>of</hi> read <hi>on.</hi> p. 15. l. 1. r. <hi>Doctrines.</hi> l. 37. r. <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi> p. 16. l. 12. r. times. p.
17. l. 6. r. <hi>ſo to that.</hi> l. 7. r. <hi>end of growth.</hi> l. 8. r.
<hi>ever and ever.</hi> p. 18. l. 18. f. <hi>it</hi> r. <hi>all.</hi> p. 19. l.
29. f. <hi>along</hi> r. <hi>alone.</hi> p. 20. l 9. f. <hi>in</hi> r.
<hi>as</hi> p. 21. l. 19. f. <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>this.</hi> l. 37. f.
<hi>ſed</hi> r. <hi>ſed</hi> p. 22. l. 14. 15. f. <hi>he witneſſes,</hi> r. <hi>bewitches.</hi> l. 27. 1. <hi>doth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45699:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
